羅馬帝國在全盛時期的版圖
由非洲沙漠延伸至
英格蘭北部邊境
羅馬皇帝更掌控了全世界
三分之一以上人口的生殺大權
在西元180年的冬天 馬可·奧勒留皇帝(著名的哲學皇帝)
12年征戰討伐日耳曼野蠻部落的行動
即將宣告結束
只要掃平最後一處據點 羅馬大軍便可獲得勝利
而帝國從此可以永享太平
日耳曼尼亞(今德國境內)
長官
Sir.
將軍
General.
長官
Sir.
士兵們又累又餓
Lean and hungry.
- 還沒有動靜嗎? - 完全沒有
- Still nothing? - Not a sign.
- 他去了多久? - 將近兩小時了
- How long has he been gone? - Nearly two hours.
他們會開戰嗎? 長官?
Will they fight, sir?
我們很快就會知道了
We shall know soon enough.
士兵 把投石車往前挪點
Soldier, I ordered you to move those catapults forward.
- 射程不夠遠 - 射程沒問題
- They're out of range. - Range is good.
- 可能會誤傷輕騎兵的... - 不用擔心 同意吧?
- The danger to the cavalry... - Is acceptable. Agreed?
他們拒絕投降
They say no.
他們應該認命了 他們已被征服了
People should know when they're conquered.
你會嗎 昆塔斯?
Would you, Quintus?
我會嗎?
Would I?
- 勇氣與榮耀 - 勇氣與榮耀
- Strength and honor. - Strength and honor.
收到我的信號後就發動攻擊
At my signal, unleash hell.
投石車準備
Load the catapults.
步兵組成進攻隊形
Infantry form up for advance.
- 弓箭手準備 - 弓箭手!
- Archers ready. - Archers!
- 搭箭! - 搭箭!
- Nock! - Nock!
弟兄們!
Fratres!
- 馬西墨斯! - 馬西墨斯!
- Maximus! - Maximus!
三星期後 我將在田里收割莊稼
Three weeks from now, I will be harvesting my crops.
想像下你要去的地方 願望就要實現了
Imagine where you will be, and it will be so.
保持隊形 跟我衝啊
Hold the line! Stay with me!
如果你發現自己落單了
If you find yourself alone,
迎著陽光 獨自馳騁在草原上時
riding in green fields with the sun on your face,
不用迷惑
do not be troubled.
那是因為你已在天堂了 你已經陣亡了
For you are in Elysium, and you're already dead!
兄弟們...
Brothers,
我們生平的事跡
what we do in life
將永遠流傳
echoes in eternity.
拉!
Pull!
投石車準備就緒 長官!
Cohorts ready, sir!
弓箭手 點火!
Archers, ignite!
- 點火! - 點火!
- Ignite! - Ignite!
弓箭手 拉滿弓!
Archers, draw!
射!
Loose!
好了 大家開始進攻
All right, men, ready!
保持隊形
Hold the line!
射!
Loose!
填裝彈藥!
Reload!
保持隊形!
Hold the line!
- 拉弓! - 射!
- Draw! - Loose!
跟著我沖!
Stay with me!
羅馬必勝!
Roma victor!
普利托裡亞十四
你認為他真的快死了嗎?
Do you think he's really dying?
十年來 他一直過都是這樣子
He's been dying for 10 years.
如果他不是快不行了 就不會派人來召見我們了
If he werert really dying, he wouldn't have sent for us.
也許他只是想念我們呢
Maybe he just misses us.
那元老會的議員們呢? 沒事他不會傳喚他們的 除非
And the senators? He wouldn't have summoned them if...
安靜點 康莫德斯
Peace, Commodus.
在路上兩星期裡
After two weeks on the road,
你老是疑神疑鬼的 煩死我了
your incessant scheming is hurting my head.
他已作了決定 他將會宣佈
He's made his decision. He's going to announce it.
傳位給我
He will name me.
我將要做的第一件事...
The first thing I shall do when...
就是舉行大型的競技比賽來榮耀他
Is honor him with games won'thy of His Majesty.
現在 我最想做的第一件事 就是淋個熱水浴
For now, the first thing I shall do is have a hot bath.
殿下?
Your Highness?
看來我們就快到了
We seem to be almost there, sir.
- 殿下 - 皇帝在哪裡?
- Sire. - Where's the Emperor?
殿下 他在前線 已經去了19天了
He's at the front, sire. They've been gone for 19 days.
傷員還在不斷的運回來
The wounded are still coming in.
備馬
My horse.
殿下
My lord.
給我一個吻?
Kiss?
你再次證明了你的勇猛 馬西墨斯
You have proved your valor yet again, Maximus.
希望這是最後一次了
Let us hope, for the last time.
我們已經沒有敵人了 陛下
There's no one left to fight, sire.
永遠不能掉以輕心 敵人無處不在
There is always someone left to fight.
我該怎樣獎賞羅馬最偉大的將軍呢?
How can I reward Rome's greatest general?
恩准我回家
Let me go home.
家
Home.
凱撒 他們向你致敬
They honor you, Caesar.
是向你致敬 馬西墨斯 他們尊敬你
It's for you, Maximus. They honor you.
我錯過了這次的戰役了嗎?
Have I missed it? Have I missed the battle?
你錯過了整場戰爭
You have missed the war.
父親 恭喜你
Father, congratulations.
我會獻上100頭公牛來慶祝你的勝利
I shall sacrifice 100 bulls to honor your triumph.
那到不必
Save the bulls.
向馬西墨斯致敬吧 是他打贏了這場戰役
Honor Maximus. He won the battle.
- 將軍 - 陛下
- General. - Highness.
羅馬向你致敬 而我以兄弟的身份擁抱你
Rome salutes you, and I embrace you as a brother.
很久沒見了 老朋友
It has been too long, my old friend.
陛下
Highness.
來 父親 讓我來扶你
Here, Father. Take my arm.
我想我是時候離開了
I think it is time for me to leave.
這就是羅馬的榮耀
So much for the glory of Rome.
宏偉的戰役
Magnificent battle.
將軍 還活著?
General. Still alive?
還活著
Still alive.
天上的諸神也有幽默感的
The gods must have a sense of humor.
- 他們一定特別照顧你 - 維勒瑞斯
- The gods must love you. - Valerius.
將軍 你是要回軍營呢? 還是回羅馬?
Back to barracks, General? Or to Rome?
回家 我妻子孩子還有莊稼都在等著我
Home. My wife, my son, the harvest.
農夫馬西墨斯 我還是無法想像你當農夫的樣子
Maximus the farmer. I still have difficulty imagining that.
你知道的 泥垢要比血跡容易洗掉 昆塔斯
You know, dirt cleans off a lot easier than blood, Quintus.
- 他在這裡 - 陛下
- Here he is. - Highness.
議員蓋爾斯 議員佛克
Senator Gaius, Senator Falco.
當心蓋爾斯 他會替你洗腦
Beware of Gaius. He'll pour a honeyed potion in your ear,
接著某天你醒來 就只會高喊"共和萬歲 共和萬歲"
and you'll wake up one day and all you'll say is, "Republic, republic, republic."
有何不可? 畢竟羅馬創建時是共和制的
Well, why not? Rome was founded as a republic.
在共和制下 共和國是由元老會來執政的
Yes, and in a republic the senate has the power.
當然 議員蓋爾斯絕不是因此才從政的
But Senator Gaius isn't influenced by that, of course.
你支持誰呢? 將軍? 皇帝還是元老院?
Where do you stand, General? Emperor or Senate?
軍人的職責就是
A soldier has the advantage
保家衛國上陣殺敵 議員
of being able to look his enemy in the eye, Senator.
有軍隊支持 你要從政易如反掌
Well, with an army behind you, you could be extremely political.
我警告了你 二位 失陪一下
I warned you. Now I shall save you. Senators.
馬西墨斯
Maximus.
我將會需要你的幫助
I'm going to need good men like you.
有什麼我可以效勞的 殿下?
How may I be of service, Highness?
只有你才知道該如何指揮軍隊
You're a man who knows what it is to command.
在你的領導下 無人不服 戰無不勝
You give your orders, the orders are obeyed, and the battle is won.
但那些議員們只會爭吵算計阿諛奉承還有欺騙
But these senators scheme, squabble and flatter and deceive.
馬西墨斯 我們必須從政客們的手中拯救羅馬
Maximus, we must save Rome from the politicians, my friend.
到時候我能期待你的幫助嗎?
Can I count on you when the time comes?
殿下 只要你父親恩准我離開 我打算立刻回家去
Highness, when your father releases me, I intend to return home.
回家? 你是應該回家看看
Home? Well, no one's earned it more.
可別耽於安逸 也許我很快就會需要你的
Don't get too comfortable. I may call on you before long.
露西拉來了 你知道嗎?
Lucilla's here. Did you know?
她還沒有忘記你
She's not forgotten you.
而現在 你是個英雄了
And now, you're the great man.
如果你生為男人的話
If only you had been born a man,
你會成為一位偉大的凱撒
what a Caesar you would have made.
父親
Father.
你會很強壯
You would have been strong.
我想知道 你會很公正嗎?
I wonder, would you have been just?
我不會辜負你對我的教導和期望
I would have been what you taught me to be.
旅途怎樣?
How was yourjourney?
漫長 不舒服 為什麼要我來?
Long. Uncomfortable. Why have I come?
我需要你的幫忙 和你弟弟有關
I need your help. With your brother.
當然
Of course.
他愛你 他一向都很愛你
He loves you. He always has.
另外
And
他現在比往常更需要你
he will need you now, more than ever.
不談政治了
Enough of politics.
我們何不假裝你是一個可愛的女兒
Let us pretend that you are a loving daughter,
而我則是個好父親
and I am a good father.
令人愉快的假設 不是嗎?
This is a pleasant fiction, isn't it?
早上好
Good morning to you.
再給我三匹馬
I need three more horses.
一! 二! 三!
One! Two! Three!
四!
Four!
一! 二!
One! Two!
你召見我嗎 凱撒?
You sent for me, Caesar?
- 凱撒? - 再告訴我一遍 馬西墨斯
- Caesar? - Tell me again, Maximus.
我們為什麼會在這裡?
Why are we here?
為了羅馬的榮耀 陛下
For the glory of the empire, sire.
沒錯
Yes.
對 我記起來了
Yes, I remember.
看到那地圖了嗎 馬西墨斯?
Do you see that map, Maximus?
那就是我所創建的世界
That is the world which I created.
25年來...
For 25 years,
我四處征戰 半生戎馬 才有今天的局面
I have conquered, spilt blood, expanded the empire.
自從我成為凱撒後 據我所知只有四年沒有戰爭
Since I became Caesar, I've known four years without war.
在20年裡 只有四年的和平
Four years of peace in 20.
這一切究竟是為了什麼?
And for what?
我只給大家帶來了戰爭 僅此而已
I brought the sword. Nothing more.
凱撒 你的一生...
Caesar, your life...
求你 不要那麼叫我了
Please. Please don't call me that.
過來
Come. Please.
過來坐下
Come sit.
讓我們好好談談
Let us talk together now,
純粹是男人之間的閒聊
very simply, as men.
說吧 馬西墨斯
Well, Maximus,
說吧
talk.
我有5000個人在外面的泥漿中挨凍
Five thousand of my men are out there in the freezing mud.
其中3000人渾身是傷
Three thousand of them are bloodied and cleaved.
另外有2000人再也無法離開這裡 他們都已經死了
Two thousand will never leave this place.
我絕不相信他們的犧牲毫無意義
I will not believe that they fought and died for nothing.
那你相信什麼 馬西墨斯?
And what would you believe?
他們為了你和羅馬而戰
They fought for you and for Rome.
羅馬是什麼 馬西墨斯?
And what is Rome, Maximus?
我到過世界上別的許多地方
I've seen much of the rest of the world.
那裡既冷酷又陰暗 羅馬象徵著光明
It is brutal and cruel and dark. Rome is the light.
但你從沒去過那裡
Yet you have never been there.
你沒看見羅馬已經變成什麼樣了
You have not seen what it has become.
我快要死了 馬西墨斯
I am dying, Maximus.
當一個快死的時候
When a man sees his end,
他會想知道自己的一生是否有價值
he wants to know there was some purpose to his life.
人們將來會怎麼評價我呢?
How will the world speak my name in years to come?
會推崇我是個哲學家?
Will I be known as the philosopher?
一名勇士?
The warrior?
還是位暴君?
The tyrant?
或是讓羅馬回歸自我的皇帝?
Or will I be the Emperor who gave Rome back her true self?
恢復共和制的羅馬是個夢想
There was once a dream that was Rome.
你只能悄悄地說
You could only whisper it.
再大聲一點的話 它將會消失
Anything more than a whisper and it would vanish,
它是如此的脆弱
it was so fragile.
我擔心在殘酷的現實環境中 他根本無法存活下去
And I fear that it will not survive the winter.
馬西墨斯
Maximus,
讓我們說點悄悄話
let us whisper now,
只有我和你
together, you and I.
你有個兒子
You have a son.
說說你講你的家庭
Tell me about your home.
我家在提基洛附近的山丘上
My house is in the hills above Trujillo.
一個非常簡單的地方
A very simple place.
在陽光下的暖和的紅磚屋
Pink stones that warm in the sun.
白天 菜園裡飄著藥草的香味
A kitchen garden that smells of herbs in the day,
到了晚上則是茉莉花的味道
jasmine in the evening.
門外有一棵高大的白楊樹
Through the gate is a giant poplar.
無花果樹 蘋果樹和梨樹
Figs, apples, pears.
土壤是黑色的 比我妻子的頭髮還黑
The soil, Marcus, black. Black like my wife's hair.
南坡上種葡萄 北坡種著橄欖
Grapes on the south slopes, olives on the north.
野生的小馬在我家附近玩耍 他們常逗我的兒子玩
Wild ponies play near my house. They tease my son.
他也想變成一匹小馬
He wants to be one of them.
你上一次回家是什麼時候?
When was the last time you were home?
2年又264天 還要算上今天早上
Two years, 264 days and this morning.
我羨慕你 馬西墨斯 你有個幸福的家庭
I envy you, Maximus. It's a good home.
值得你為它如此奮鬥
Worth fighting for
在你回家之前
There is one more duty
我希望你幫我做最後一件事
that I ask of you before you go home.
你要我做什麼 凱撒?
What would you have me do, Caesar?
我要你在我死後成為羅馬的保護者
I want you to become the protector of Rome after I die.
我會把政權交給你
I will empower you to one end alone,
將權力還給羅馬的人民
to give power back to the people of Rome,
結束危害羅馬的貪污腐敗
and end the corruption that has crippled it.
你願意接受這光榮的使命嗎?
Will you accept this great honor that I have offered you?
我打心眼裡...不願意
With all my heart, no.
馬西墨斯
Maximus,
這就是我一定要授權給你的原因
that is why it must be you.
但這應該是行政官或者議員的職責
But surely a prefect, a senator,
一個瞭解羅馬 熟悉政治的人
somebody who knows the city, who understands her politics.
但你還沒被羅馬的政治腐蝕
But you have not been corrupted by her politics.
- 康莫德斯呢? - 康莫德斯不是正人君子
- And Commodus? - Commodus is not a moral man.
你比誰都要清楚這一點
You have known that since you were young.
康莫德斯不能統治羅馬
Commodus cannot rule.
絕對不可以
He must not rule.
我要是有你這樣的兒子就好了
You are the son that I should have had.
康莫德斯會接受我的決定的
Commodus will accept my decision.
他知道軍隊只對你效忠
He knows that you command the loyalty of the army.
我需要時間考慮
I need some time, sire.
好吧
Yes.
我希望在日落之前你能答應我的請求
By sunset, I hope you will have agreed.
現在 象兒子般擁抱我吧
Now embrace me as my son.
順便再幫我拿條毯子來
And bring an old man another blanket.
- 我父親現在只寵愛你 - 夫人
- My father favors you now. - My lady.
- 以前不是這樣 - 很多東西都改變了
- It was not always so. - Many things change.
話是沒錯 但不是所有的事情
Many things. Not everything.
馬西墨斯 站住
Maximus, stop.
讓我看看你的臉
Let me see your face.
- 你看起來很沮喪 - 我失去了很多部下
- You seem upset. - I lost many men.
我父親找你有什麼事?
What did my father want with you?
在我回家前祝我一路順風
To wish me well before I leave for home.
你在撒謊
You're lying.
我總能看穿你在撒謊 因為你不精於此道
I could always tell when you were lying, because you were never any good at it.
我一直都不習慣你的安慰
I never acquired your comfort with it.
沒錯
True.
反正你也不需要
But then you never had to.
對軍人來說 生活要簡單的多
Life is more simple for a soldier.
或許你覺得我很無情?
Or do you think me heartless?
我覺得你具備生存的天分
I think you have a talent for survival.
馬西墨斯 停下
Maximus, stop.
再次見到我真的這麼可怕嗎?
Is it really so terrible seeing me again?
不 我只是厭倦了戰爭
No. I'm tired from battle.
看到我父親是那麼脆弱 你很心痛
It hurts you to see my father so fragile.
康莫德斯期望父親會很快宣佈他是斷任者
Commodus expects that my father will announce his succession within days.
你會像追隨我父親那樣對我弟弟效忠嗎?
Will you serve my brother as you served his father?
我會永遠對羅馬效忠
I will always serve Rome.
你知道嗎
Do you know,
我還是不忘替你祈禱
I still remember you in my prayers.
是的 我有祈禱
Oh, yes. I pray.
聽到你丈夫去世的消息我很難過 我替他追悼
I was sad to hear of your husband's death. I mourned him.
- 謝謝你 - 我聽說你有個兒子
- Thank you. - And I hear you have a son.
是 他叫盧修斯
Yes. Lucius.
他快八歲了
He'll be nearly eight years old.
我兒子也快八歲
My son is also nearly eight.
謝謝你的祈禱
I thank you for your prayers.
祖先們 我祈求你們指引我
Ancestors, I ask for your guidance.
天上的母親 求你指示我未來的方向
Blessed Mother, come to me with the gods' desire for my future.
天上的父親 求您保佑我的妻兒
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son with a ready sword.
請轉告他們 我只是為再次擁抱他們而活
Whisper to them, I live only to hold them again.
祖先們 我榮耀你們
Ancestors, I honor you,
並將謹遵祖訓 有尊嚴的活下去
and will try to live with the dignity you have taught me.
西斯洛
Cicero.
主人
Sir.
我不覺得履行義務很困難嗎?
Do you ever find it hard to do your duty?
有時我做我想做事
Sometimes I do what I want to do.
其餘的時間我做我應該做的事
The rest of the time, I do what I have to.
也許我們還是不能回家去
We may not be able to go home, after all.
你準備好對羅馬履行你的職責了嗎?
Are you ready to do your duty for Rome?
是的 父親
Yes, Father.
你不會成為皇帝
You will not be emperor.
哪位年長的智者會取代我的地位?
Which wiser, older man is to take my place?
我會將政權移交給馬西墨斯
My powers will pass to Maximus,
直到確認
to hold in trust,
元老院準備好再次治理羅馬
until the Senate is ready to rule once more.
羅馬會再度成為共和國
Rome is to be a republic again.
- 馬西墨斯 - 對
- Maximus. - Yes.
我的決定使你失望了嗎?
My decision disappoints you?
你曾寫信給我
You wrote to me once,
上面列舉了四種主要的美德
listing the four chief virtues.
智慧...
Wisdom,
公正...
justice,
堅毅...
fortitude,
和自律
and temperance.
讀完信後我就明白自己一種都不具備
As I read the list, I knew I had none of them.
但我有其他的美德 父親
But I have other virtues, Father.
野心
Ambition.
當它驅使我們做的更優秀的時候 這也是一種美德
That can be a virtue when it drives us to excel.
智謀 勇氣
Resourcefulness, courage.
也許和行軍打仗無關 但...勇氣也有很多種的
Perhaps not on the battlefield, but there are many forms of courage.
對家庭的全心全意的奉獻...
Devotion to my family,
還有對你的愛
to you.
但你完全不欣賞我所有的優點
But none of my virtues were on your list.
就像你根本不希望有我這樣的兒子
Even then it was as if you didn't want me for your son.
康莫德斯
Commodus,
你想的太多了
you go too far.
我向天上的諸神祈求...
I searched the faces of the gods
讓我能夠討你歡心 讓你能夠以我為榮
for ways to please you, to make you proud.
只要一句讚美
One kind word,
或是一個擁抱...
one full hug,
把我緊緊的抱在你懷裡
where you pressed me to your chest and held me tight,
都會像慈藹的陽光溫暖我的心
would have been like the sun on my heart for 1, 000 years.
為什麼你如此討厭我?
What is it in me you hate so much?
康莫德斯
Commodus.
我不敢有任何奢求...
All I've ever wanted
只求能符合你的期望 凱撒
was to live up to you, Caesar.
- 父親 - 康莫德斯...
- Father. - Commodus,
養子不教...
your faults as a son
實為我作為父親的過錯啊
is my failure as a father.
過來
Come.
父親
Father.
為了讓你能愛我...
I would butcher the whole world,
即使血洗天下我也在所不惜!
if you would only have loved me!
馬西墨斯 皇帝有急事要找你
Maximus, the Emperor needs you. It's urgent.
和我一起哀悼 兄弟
Lament with me, brother.
我們偉大的父親去世了
Our great father is dead.
他怎樣死的?
How did he die?
醫生們說是呼吸衰竭
The surgeons say there was no pain.
他在睡夢中安詳的走了
His breath gave out as he slept.
父親
Father.
新皇帝需要你的忠誠 馬西墨斯
Your emperor asks for your loyalty, Maximus.
宣誓效忠於我
Take my hand.
我只給你一次機會
I only offer it once.
昆塔斯
Quintus.
凱撒萬歲
Hail, Caesar.
我要去見議員們 我需要他們的意見
I must talk to the senators. I need their counsel.
- 去叫醒蓋爾斯和佛克 - 蓋爾斯和佛克
- Wake Gaius and Falco. - Gaius and Falco.
- 我的劍 - 劍
- Sword. - Sword.
馬西墨斯 請三思而行 你的舉動太過輕率
Maximus, please be careful. That was not prudent.
輕率? 皇帝是被人謀殺的
Prudent? The Emperor has been slain.
皇帝是自然死亡
The emperor died of natural causes.
- 你為什麼全副武裝 昆塔斯? - 守衛!
- Why are you armed, Quintus? - Guards!
請不要反抗 馬西墨斯請不要反抗 馬西墨斯
Please don't fight, Maximus.
我很抱歉 是凱撒下的命令
I'm sorry. Caesar has spoken.
騎馬西行...
Ride until dawn,
在拂曉前處死他
and then execute him.
昆塔斯 看著我 看著我!
Quintus, look at me. Look at me!
答應我 你會好好照顧我的家人
Promise me that you will look after my family.
你的家人會在黃泉路上與你相會的
Your family will meet you in the afterlife.
跪下
Kneel.
天上的父親 請保護我的妻子和兒子
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son.
轉告他們我只為再次擁抱他們而活
Whisper to them that I live only to hold them again.
至少讓我死的痛快點
At least give me a clean death.
一個軍人式的死亡
A soldier's death.
有時候 霜會把刀刃粘住的
The frost, sometimes it makes the blade stick.
禁衛兵!
Praetorian!
你上次回家是什麼時候?
When was the last time you were home?
2年264天 再算上今天早晨
Two years, 264 days and this morning.
天上的父親 求您保佑我的妻兒
Blessed Father, watch over my wife and son with a ready sword.
我會嘗試像你教導一樣有尊嚴地生活
I will try to live with the dignity you have taught me.
告訴他們 我生存是為了再次擁抱他們
Whisper to them, I live only to hold them again.
世間名利 於我皆如糞土
...with a ready sword, for all else is dust and air.
告訴他們 我生存是為了再次擁抱他們
Whisper to them, I live only to hold them again.
世間名利 於我皆如糞土
For all else is dust and air.
爸爸!
Papa!
你不能死
Don't die.
你們會再見面的
You'll meet them again.
現在還不是時候
Not yet.
不! 他們能潔淨你的傷口 等著瞧吧
No. They will clean it. Wait and see.
千萬別死
Don't die.
他們會拿你喂獅子的
They'll feed you to the lions.
它們比我們更值錢
They are won'th more than we are.
好點吧?
Better now?
看見了嗎? 傷口已經消炎了
Clean. You see?
祖卡巴 羅馬領地
普羅西莫! 我的老朋友
Proximo! My old friend.
每次只要你來這裡 那天就一定會是個好日子
Every day is a great day when you are here,
今天...是你最幸運的一天
but today is your most fortunate day.
你賣給我的那些長頸鹿...根本不會交配
Those giraffes you sold me, they won't mate.
他們只會走來走去吃東西卻不交配
Theyjust walk around eating and not mating.
你賣給我的長頸鹿是同性戀
You sold me queer giraffes.
- 快把錢退還給我 - 不可能
- I want my money back. - Not a chance.
- 我給你好價錢 - 什麼貨?
- I do special price for you. - On what?
你看過我的新貨了嗎? 去看看吧
Have you seen my new stock? Come and see them.
他們有誰懂得搏鬥嗎? 我最近會有一場比賽
Do any of them fight? I've got a match coming up.
有些人善於搏鬥 其他人只會去送死
Some are good for fighting, others for dying.
我想兩種人你都需要
You need both, I think.
站起來!
Get up.
你以前是幹什麼的?
What's your trade?
我是獵人
I was a hunter.
不 我是在迦太基附近的鹽礦場把他買來的
No, I bought him from a salt mine in Can'thage.
坐下
Sit down.
軍團的標記
Mark of the legion.
- 逃兵 - 也許是吧 有誰在乎呢?
- Deserter. - Maybe so, but who cares?
他是個西班牙人
He's a Spaniard.
我要六個人... 給你1000
I'll take six. For 1, 000.
一千? 那個努米底亞人就值2000了
1, 000? The Numidian alone is won'th 2, 000.
這群奴隸根本不中用
These slaves are rotten.
人不可貌相 不 不 不 不 等等
It all adds to the flavor. No, no, no, wait! Wait!
等一下! 價錢好商量
I can negotiate.
我給你2000...另外給4000買那些野獸
I'll give you 2, 000, and 4, 000 for the beasts.
既然是老朋友 一共給你5000
That's 5, 000 for an old friend.
快一點! 還有多久才能回到家?
Come on! How long does it take to get into my own house?
我是普羅西莫!
I am Proximo.
接下來的幾天 將是你們悲慘的日子...
I shall be closer to you for the next few days,
結束前的最後的幾天 我會和你們異常的親近
which will be the last of your miserable lives,
勝過把你們帶到這世界來的該死的母親!
than that bitch of a mother that brought you screaming into this world.
我不是花錢買你們來做伴的!
I did not pay good money for you for your company.
我出錢是為了從你們的死亡中獲利
I paid it so that I could profit from your death.
你們的人生開始時 有母親在旁邊
And as your mother was there at your beginning,
結束時 我會在你們的身旁
so I shall be there at your end.
等到死亡的命運降臨時
And when you die, and die you shall,
你們將因人們的歡呼而昇華
your transition shall be to the sound of...
角鬥士們
Gladiators,
我向你們致敬
I salute you.
紅色
Red.
黃色
Yellow.
很好
Good.
紅色
- Red. - Red.
西班牙人!
Spaniard.
到此為止!
That's enough for the moment!
他遲早得認命的
His time will come.
下一個!
Next.
西班牙佬
Spaniard,
你為什麼不還手?
why don't you fight?
我們必須要搏鬥
We all have to fight.
我決不搏鬥
Well, I don't fight.
我不應在這裡 我是書吏 我負責記錄...
I shouldn't be here, I'm a scribe, I write down words,
我會說七種語言
and speak seven languages.
那好
Good.
明天你可用七種語言尖叫
Tomorrow, you can scream in seven languages.
或許書吏是例外 可以贏取自由
Perhaps the scribe will be the one who wins his freedom.
自由?
Freedom?
我需要做什麼?
What do I have to do?
你進競技場 殺了我
You go in the arena and you kill me.
還有他...
And him,
和這努米底亞人...
and the Numidian,
和這逃兵
and the deserter.
再多100個人
And 100 more.
直到你殺了所有鬥士 你便自由了
And when there's no more to fight, you're free.
我做不到
I can't do that.
做不到?
No?
但我做得到
But I can.
那是你信奉的神嗎?
Is that the sign of your gods?
這樣做他們不會生氣嗎?
Will that not anger them?
神眷顧你
The gods favor you.
紅色是天神的顏色
Red is the gods' color.
今天你會需要他們幫助
You will need their help today.
普羅西莫!
Proximo!
一直是日耳曼領導的?
Still leading with the German?
觀眾喜歡野蠻人
The crowd love a barbarian.
而且他令我富有
Besides that, he's making me rich.
那努米底亞人搏鬥過沒有?
Has that Numidian fought before?
沒有 第一次
No, first time.
那個 是奴隸 士兵?
And that one, laborer, soldier?
他是西班牙人
He's a Spaniard.
在場上像個廢人一樣
He might as well be a eunuch for what he brings to the ring.
五百元買努米底亞人 和西班牙人那隊會過關
500 sestertii, the Numidian and Spaniard team makes it through.
一千元 如果努米底亞人獨自過關
And 1, 000, that the Numidian makes it through alone.
你要我買自己的人輸?
Are you asking me to bet against my own man?
那是不道德的
It's unethical.
如果我加到二千元呢?
What if I make it 2, 000?
你們當中有些人不願意上場搏鬥
Some of you are thinking you won't fight,
有些覺得你不能搏鬥
some that you can't fight.
他們都喜歡唱高調 除非真正輪到自己出場
They all say that until they're out there.
你們聽
Listen.
- 殺! 殺! 殺! - 殺! 殺! 殺!
- Kill! Kill! Kill! - Kill! Kill! Kill!
把刀用力刺進別人的身體裡
Thrust this into another mars flesh,
觀眾會為此而向你喝彩 崇拜你
and they will applaud and love you for that.
而你...
And you,
你也會開始為了喝彩聲...
you may begin to love them
而愛上他們
for that.
最終 我們都會化為一堆枯骨
Ultimately, we're all dead men.
可悲的是 我們無權選擇命運 但...
Sadly, we cannot choose how,
有權決定如何面對死亡...
but we can decide how we meet that end,
惟有如此 才能作為人
in order that we are remembered
被人們追憶
as men.
快!
Come on!
左邊的 拿盾牌!
On the left, draw your shields!
右邊的 拿劍!
On the right, draw your swords!
- 殺! 殺! - 殺! 殺!
- Kill! Kill! Kill! - Kill! Kill! Kill!
兩人一組 紅色和黃色一起
Pair them up, red with yellow.
下一個!
Next!
打!
Move!
奪權者!
Usurper!
- 滾開! - 我們不要你統治 康莫德斯!
- Go away! - You'll never rule us, Commodus!
他像個凱旋的英雄般回到羅馬 但他到底征服了什麼呢?
He enters Rome like a conquering hero. But what has he conquered?
給他點時間 格瑞克斯 他還年輕
Give him time, Gracchus. He's young.
我相信他可以做的很好
I think he could do very well.
為羅馬還是為你?
For Rome, or for you?
盧修斯 去歡迎你的母親 她會很高興的
Go to your mother, Lucius. It's what she'd like.
- 盧修斯! - 媽媽!
- Lucius! - Mother!
向你致敬 凱撒
Hail, Caesar.
議員們
Senators.
羅馬歡迎她的新皇帝
Rome greets her new emperor.
你忠心的臣子們向你表示歡迎 陛下
Your loyal subjects bid you welcome, Highness.
謝謝你 佛克
Thank you, Falco.
說到忠心的子民 我相信他們並不太昂貴
And for the loyal subjects, I trust they werert too expensive.
- 凱撒 - 格瑞克斯
- Caesar. - Gracchus.
羅馬為你的歸來而歡呼 凱撒
All Rome rejoices in your return, Caesar.
有許多政務等你來處理
But there are many matters that require your attention.
請肅靜! 肅靜!
To order, please. To order.
凱撒 為了請你指引
For your guidance, Caesar,
凱撒 元老院已經擬訂一系列的議程 好方便陛下過目...
the Senate has prepared a series of protocols
開始解決城市裡的眾多問題
to begin addressing the many problems in the city,
首先是希臘區的基礎衛生設備...
beginning with basic sanitation for the Greek Quarter,
設法消滅該區正在蔓延的瘟疫
to combat the plague which is already springing up there.
所以 如果凱撒...
So, if Caesar...
你難道還不明白 格瑞克斯?
Don't you see, Gracchus?
這才是問題的重點 不是嗎?
That's the very problem, isn't it?
我父親花費畢生的時間...
My father spent all his time at study,
研讀書本中的知識和哲學
at books of learning and philosophy.
他的晚年盡在閱讀元老院的卷軸中度過
He spent his twilight hours reading scrolls from the Senate.
然而自始至終 他卻忽略了人民...
And all the while, the people were forgotten.
但元老會就代表人民 陛下
But the senate is the people, sire,
由人民中選出議員 為人民說話
chosen from among the people to speak for the people.
我懷疑民眾是否像你一樣豐衣足食 格瑞克斯
I doubt many of the people eat so well as you do, Gracchus.
或是像蓋爾斯一樣妻妾成群
Or have such splendid mistresses, Gaius.
我自認瞭解我的子民
I think I understand my own people.
那麼 根據您個人的多方面的經驗...
Then perhaps Caesar will be so good as to teach us,
陛下或許會不吝賜教
out of his own extensive experience.
我認為是愛
I call it love.
我會愛民如子 因為他們都是我的子民
I am their father. The people are my children.
我會將他們緊緊的擁抱在我的胸前
And I shall hold them to my bosom and embrace them tightly.
陛下 你曾擁抱過身染瘟疫的人嗎?
Have you ever embraced someone dying of plague, sire?
沒有 但如果你再打斷我的話
No, but if you interrupt me again,
我保證你一定會的
I assure you that you shall.
議員 我弟弟非常疲倦
Senator, my brother is very tired.
把議程給我 凱撒應該照人民的意願行事
Leave your list with me. Caesar shall do all that Rome requires.
夫人 你總是讓人不能不服
My lady, as always, your lightest touch commands obedience.
他們憑什麼對我說教?
Who are they to lecture me?
康莫德斯 元老院自有它的用處
Commodus, the Senate has its uses.
什麼用處? 他們只會耍嘴皮子
What uses? All they do is talk.
根本就只需要...你和我...
It should be just you and me and Rome.
千萬不可以這麼想! 元老院自建國之初就存在著
Don't even think it. There's always been a Senate.
羅馬已經變了
Rome has changed.
只要有一個皇帝...就可以治理帝國了
It takes an emperor to rule an empire.
當然 讓人民繼續擁有...
Of course, but leave the people their...
幻想
Illusions?
傳統
Traditions.
我父親對野蠻人發動戰爭...
My father's war against the barbarians.
他自己也承認那毫無意義 但是人民敬愛他
He said it himself, it achieved nothing. But the people loved him.
人民總是喜歡勝利的感覺的
The people always love victories.
為什麼? 他們並沒有目睹戰爭的殘酷
Why? They didn't see the battles.
日耳曼人和他們毫不相關
What do they care about Germania?
他們只關心羅馬的富強
They care about the greatness of Rome.
"羅馬的富強"
"The greatness of Rome."
那到底是什麼呢?
Well, what is that?
是一種理念... 富強
It's an idea. Greatness.
- 富強是一種憧憬 - 沒錯 一個憧憬
- Greatness is a vision. - Exactly. A vision.
你還不明白嗎 露西拉?
Do you not see, Lucilla?
我會給人民一個羅馬的新憧憬 他們會為此而敬愛我
I will give the people a vision of Rome, and they'll love me for it.
他們很快就會忘掉那幾個愛說教的老頭
And they'll soon forget the tedious sermonizing of a few dry old men.
我會給羅馬人民一個前所未有的憧憬
I will give the people the greatest vision of their lives.
鬥士 - 暴力
酒 酒 酒! 紅酒白酒任君暢飲!
White and red wine for your drinking pleasure!
競技
Games.
整整150天的競技活動
One hundred and fifty days of games.
他比我想像中的要聰明
He's cleverer than I thought.
聰明 要不是因為害怕他的禁衛隊...
Clever. The whole of Rome would be laughing at him,
全羅馬的人都會嘲笑他的
if they werert so afraid of his Praetorians.
害怕和好奇...強而有力的組合
Fear and wonder. A powerful combination.
你真的認為民眾會被他的手段所欺騙?
You really think the people are going to be seduced by that?
我覺得他瞭解羅馬的本質 羅馬是由一群烏合之眾組成的
I think he knows what Rome is. Rome is the mob.
變魔術給他們看 就可以轉移他們的注意力
Conjure magic for them, and they'll be distracted.
奪去他們的自由 他們還是會繼續哄堂大笑
Take away their freedom, and still they'll roar.
維繫著羅馬命脈的...並不是元老院裡的大理石
The beating heart of Rome is not the marble of the Senate.
而是競技場內的沙地
It's the sand of the Colosseum.
他會把死亡帶給人民
He'll bring them death,
而人民會為此而敬愛他
and they will love him for it.
你只需殺殺殺
All you do is kill, kill, kill.
觀眾不是要屠夫 他們要英雄
The crowd don't want a butcher, they want a hero.
我們要他們不斷回來看
We want them to keep coming back.
所以不要只顧把他們斬殺 記著你是要娛樂觀眾
So don't just hack them to pieces, remember you are an entertainer.
西班牙人
Spaniard.
快去娛樂他們!
So entertain!
你們還不滿意嗎? 你們還不滿意嗎?
Are you not entertained? Are you not entertained?
你們不正是為此而來這裡的嗎?
Is this not why you're here?
西班牙人!
Spaniard! Spaniard! Spaniard!
- 西班牙人! 西班牙人! 西班牙人! - 西班牙人! 西班牙人! 西班牙人!
- Spaniard! Spaniard! Spaniard! - Spaniard! Spaniard! Spaniard!
你想要些什麼?
What do you want?
女孩?
Girl?
男孩?
Boy?
- 你找我有事? - 是的
- You sent for me. - Yes, I did.
西班牙人 你的確很棒 但你還不是最厲害的
You're good, Spaniard, but you're not that good.
你可以變的更優秀
You could be magnificent.
我殺人是因為你要我這麼做 這樣就夠了
I'm required to kill, so I kill. That is enough.
也許在鄉下小地方是夠了 但在羅馬卻行不通
That's enough for the provinces, but not for Rome.
那年輕皇帝安排了一系列表演...
The young emperor has arranged a series of spectacles
來紀念他的父親 馬可·奧勒留
to commemorate his father, Marcus Aurelius.
我覺得很好笑...
I find that amusing,
因為正是馬可·奧勒留...
since it was Marcus Aurelius, the wise,
博學 無所不知的馬可·奧勒留...禁止了搏鬥競技活動
the all-knowing Marcus Aurelius, that closed us down.
在這個跳蚤為患的村莊...
So finally, after five years of scratching a living
生活了五年以後
in flea-infested villages,
我們終於要回到屬於我們的地方...
we're finally going back to where we belong.
羅馬競技場
The Colosseum.
你應該去看看競技場 西班牙人
You should see the Colosseum, Spaniard.
五萬羅馬觀眾...
Fifty thousand Romans,
注視著你鬥劍時的一舉一動
watching every movement of your sword,
期待你揮出致命的一擊
willing you to make that killer blow.
在你揮劍之前的寂靜...和那之後的騷動
The silence before you strike and the noise afterwards.
喧鬧聲不斷的提高...
It rises. It rises up,
就像...一場暴風雨...
like a storm.
而你自己就是雷神
As if you were the thunder god himself.
- 你曾是個角鬥士? - 對 我是
- You were a gladiator? - Yes, I was.
你贏得了你的自由?
You won your freedom?
很久以前 皇帝...
A long time ago, the Emperor
送給我一把劍
presented me with a rudius.
那只是一把木劍
It's just a wooden sword.
你得到自由的象徵
The symbol of your freedom.
他用木劍點了點我的肩 我便獲得了自由
He touched me on the shoulder, and I was free.
你認識馬可·奧勒留?
You knew Marcus Aurelius?
我沒說我認識他 我說他曾經碰過我的肩膀
I did not say I knew him. I said he touched me on the shoulder once.
你問我到底想要什麼
You asked me what I want.
我也希望站在皇帝面前...
I, too, want to stand in front of the Emperor,
就像你一樣
as you did.
那你就得聽我的 向我學習
Then listen to me. Learn from me.
我並不是最棒的 因為我殺人太快了
I wasrt the best because I killed quickly.
我之所以是最棒的 是因為民眾崇拜我
I was the best because the crowd loved me.
贏取觀眾的心 你就能贏得自由
Win the crowd, and you'll win your freedom.
我會贏得觀眾的心
I will win the crowd.
我將讓他們看見從未見過的東西!
I will give them something they've never seen before.
那麼 西班牙人 我們一起去羅馬
So, Spaniard, we shall go to Rome together
展開一趟血腥的冒險!
and have bloody adventures.
觀眾會讓我們的荷包撐滿...
And the great whore will suckle us
開心的笑不出來
until we are fat and happy and can suckle no more.
然後...
And then,
殺了足夠多的人後
when enough men have died,
也許你就可以得到你的自由
perhaps you will have your freedom.
接著 這個給你
Here. Use this.
在遠處的某個地方...有我的祖國
It's somewhere out there, my country.
我的家
My home.
我的妻子正在準備食物
My wife is preparing food.
我的女兒從河邊打水回來
My daughters carry water from the river.
我還能再見到他們嗎?
Will I ever see them again?
我想沒機會了
I think, no.
你相信死後能再見到他們嗎?
Do you believe you'll see them again when you die?
我相信
I think so.
但是 我很快就會死了
But then, I will die soon.
他們會再活很多年
They will not die for many years.
我得等他們
I'll have to wait.
但是你願意...等
But you would? Wait?
當然
Of course.
你知道的
You see,
我的妻兒...
my wife and my son
已經在等著我了
are already waiting for me.
你會再見到他們的 只是時候未到
You'll meet them again. But not yet.
時候未到
Not yet.
- 除非... - 時候未到
- Unless... - Not yet.
時候未到
Not yet.
他在那裡
There he is.
出來!
Out.
快出來!
Move, go, out!
老朋友 真高興又看見你
Good to see you again, old friend.
帶給我財富
Bring me fortune.
你以前看見過這麼壯觀的建築嗎?
Have you ever seen anything like that before?
我不知道他們是如何辦到的
I didn't know men could build such things.
贏得觀眾的心
Win the crowd.
快進去! 走
Get inside. Move.
進去
Inside.
他睡的好香因為他備受寵愛
He sleeps so well because he's loved.
走吧 弟弟 已經很晚了
Come, brother. It's late.
我將使羅馬成為當代的奇跡
I will make Rome the wonder of the ages.
那是格瑞克斯和他的朋友所不明白的
That is what Gracchus and his friends don't understand.
我的慾望在腦海中起伏 讓我頭痛欲裂
All my desires are splitting my head to pieces.
康莫德斯 喝了這蘇打水
Commodus, drink this tonic.
我看時機已經成熟
I think the time is almost right.
我可以在悼念父親的慶典上...
I could announce the dissolution of the Senate
宣佈解散元老院
at the celebration to honor our father.
你認為我該這麼做嗎?
Do you think I should?
人民能接受嗎?
Are the people ready?
我想你現在需要休息
I think you need your rest now.
你會不會留下來陪我?
Will you stay with me?
弟弟 你還是怕黑嗎?
Still afraid of the dark, brother?
是的
Still.
永遠都怕
Always.
- 今晚留下來陪我? - 你知道那不可能
- Stay with me tonight. - You know I won't.
那就吻我一下
Then kiss me.
晚安 弟弟
Sleep, brother.
又聾又啞的僕人...
Having servants who are deaf and mute
至少讓我活得久一點
at least ensures I live a little longer.
他們在拘捕學者
They're arresting scholars now.
任何敢表達意見的 甚至包括作家和史學家
Anyone who dare speak out. Even satirists and chroniclers.
還有數學家
And mathematicians.
全部送到鬥獸場
And all to feed the arena.
國會沒有通過戒嚴法
The Senate did not approve martial law.
這全是禁衛軍的恐怖勢力
This reign of terror is entirely the Praetorians.
我入黑後不敢外出
I'm afraid to go out after dark.
你更應擔心日間的出行
You should be more afraid of your activities during the day.
國會中佈滿他的線眼 由那好色的科高領導的
The Senate is full of his spies, led by that whore master, Falco.
究竟他在想什麼? 那是最令我困惑的
But what is in his mind? That's what I trouble myself with.
他整天只顧...
He spends all his days singularly obsessed,
籌劃你父親的紀念慶典
planning the festival to honor your father.
他連政府最基本的工作也忽略
He neglects even the most fundamental task of government.
他到底在計劃什麼?
So just what is he planning?
用什麼來支付?
And what pays for it?
每天這些競技支出龐大 但我們沒加新稅項
These daily games are costing a fortune, yet we have no new taxes.
未來
The future.
用未來支付
The future pays for it.
他已開始賣貯備的穀物
He's started selling the grain reserves.
不是吧
This can't be true.
他在賣羅馬貯備的穀物
He's selling Rome's reserves of grain.
人民在兩年後便會捱餓
The people will be starving in two years.
希望他們享受這遊戲...
I hope they're enjoying the games,
那些競技不久他們便會因此而滅亡
because soon enough they'll be dead because of them.
- 羅馬人要知道真相 - 怎樣?
- Rome must know this. - And how?
他打算解散國會
He's going to dissolve the Senate.
誰會及時告訴他們? 你 格瑞克斯?
And who will tell them before it's too late? You, Gracchus?
你 蓋爾斯
You, Gaius.
你會否在國會上發表演說
Will you make a speech on the floor of the Senate,
指責我哥哥?
denouncing my brother?
然後看著你全家被推進鬥獸場?
And then see your family in the Colosseum?
誰敢?
Who'd dare?
我每天都活在恐懼中...
I have been living in a prison of fear every day,
因為我兒子是皇位繼承人
because my son is heir to the throne.
他一定要死
He must die.
但昆塔斯和禁衛軍會奪去控制權
Quintus and the Praetorians would simply seize control for themselves.
不 把領導者殺了就不會失去控制權
No. Cut off the head and the snake cannot strike.
露西娜 蓋爾斯說得對
Lucilla, Gaius is right.
不能壓制禁衛軍的話 我們不會成功
Until we can neutralize the Praetorians, we can achieve nothing.
那我們坐以待斃?
So we do nothing?
不 我們在暗中計劃
No, child. We keep our counsel.
我們準備
We prepare.
人民支持他 我們的聲音便沒有力量
As long as the people support him, we are voices without steel.
我們是空氣
We are air.
但每天他都在豎敵
But with every day that passes, he makes enemies.
終有一天 他的敵人會多過朋友
One day, he'll have more enemies than friends.
那就是我們行動的時候
And on that day, we will act.
那時我們便反擊
Then we will strike.
在那刻來臨前...
But until then,
我們是聽話的
we are docile.
我們是服從的
We are obedient.
而我們亦是不忠的
And we are treacherous.
快!
Come on!
好了 夠了
All right, that's enough.
皇帝想看搏鬥
The Emperor wants battles,
但我不想犧牲最好的鬥士
and I don't want to sacrifice my best fighters.
觀眾想看競技 所以皇帝就舉辦大型的競技搏鬥
The crowd wants battles, so the Emperor gives them battles.
- 你的人將參加迦太基的戰役 - 迦太基的大屠殺
- You get the battle of Can'thage. - Massacre of Can'thage.
你為什麼不把監獄裡的
Well, why don't you go down to the prison,
乞丐小偷都找來?
round up all the beggars and thieves?
我們早就這麼做了
We've done that.
如果你想要我犧牲
If you want to give away the best gladiators
全帝國最棒的角鬥士
in the whole of the empire,
就得給我雙倍的錢
then I want double the rates.
我們要麼按照合約給錢 要麼就取消合約
You'll get your contract rates, or you'll get your contract canceled.
你不高興嗎?
You don't like it?
那就滾回你的老家去
Then you can crawl back down that shit hole that you came from.
等等 卡西亞斯!
Cassius, please. You can free us.
你就是外號"西班牙人"的角鬥士嗎?
Gladiator, are you the one they call the Spaniard?
是的
Yes.
他們都說你力大無窮
They said you were a giant.
他們說你單手就能捏碎大人的頭
They said you could crush a mars skull with one hand.
大人的? 不可能
A mars? No.
小孩的也許可以
A boy's.
- 西班牙有良種馬嗎? - 有最優秀的馬
- Do they have good horses in Spain? - Some of the best.
這是銀子 這是黑點
This is Argento and this is Scan'to.
他們是我的馬
They were my horses.
可是被別人搶走了
They were taken from me.
我很喜歡你 西班牙人 我會替你加油的
I like you, Spaniard. I shall cheer for you.
- 他們准你看競技比賽? - 我舅舅說這會使我變得勇敢
- They let you watch the games? - My uncle says it makes me strong.
- 那你父親怎樣說? - 我父親死了
- And what does your father say? - My father is dead.
盧修斯少爺 該走了
Master Lucius, it is time.
我得走了
I have to go.
你叫盧修斯?
Your name is Lucius?
盧修斯維勒斯 為了紀念我父親
Lucius Verus, after my father.
往下放!
Lower!
- 哥地亞斯! - 是?
- Claudius! - Yes?
- 克勞迪亞斯! 還要更多的盾牌! - 好的 長官
- More shields! - All right.
當皇上進場時 舉起你們的武器向他致敬
When the Emperor enters, raise your weapons, salute him,
然後齊聲向他問候!
and then speak together.
面對著皇帝 不可以背對著他!
Face the Emperor and don't turn your back on him.
去吧! 為榮譽而戰!
Go, and die with honor.
歡迎偉大的凱撒!
Hail, mighty Caesar!
- 凱撒萬歲! 凱撒萬歲! - 凱撒萬歲! 凱撒萬歲!
- Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! - Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
- 角鬥士們向您致敬! - 角鬥士們向您致敬!
- We who are about to die salute you! - We who are about to die salute you!
今天...
On this day
我們把戰場移到神聖的古代...
we reach back to hallowed antiquity
呈現在各位面前的是...
to bring you a re-creation of the second fall
迦太基淪亡的歷史戰役!
of mighty Can'thage!
在荒蕪的扎馬平原上...
On the barren plain of Zama
漢尼拔將軍的...
there stood the invincible armies
不可戰勝的野蠻人軍隊正嚴陣以待
of the barbarian Hannibal.
來自所有殘暴民族的...
Ferocious mercenaries and warriors
傭兵和戰士們...
from all brute nations,
毫不留情的破壞
bent on merciless destruction,
征服
conquest.
你們的皇帝很榮幸的為大家介紹...
Your emperor is pleased to give you
野蠻的異幫人!
the barbarian horde!
有人在軍隊裡服役過嗎?
Anyone here been in the army?
有 我曾在凡度巴納和你一起服役
Yes. I served with you at Vindobona.
你可以幫我忙
You can help me.
不管從鐵門後出現的是什麼
Whatever comes out of these gates,
我們只有同心協力才會有較大的勝算
we've got a better chance of survival ifwe work together.
你明白嗎?
Do you understand?
只有團結一致 我們才能活命
Lfwe stay together, we survive.
我很榮幸為你們介紹...
The Emperor is pleased to bring you the legionnaires
非洲的西比歐軍團
of Scipio Africanus!
奮戰到底!
To the death!
- 殺! 殺! 殺! - 殺! 殺! 殺!
- Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill! - Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill!
大家靠攏!
Stay close.
集合起來!
Come together!
縱隊交錯排列!
Stay close. Staggered columns!
你沒機會了!
You don't have a chance.
固定盾牌! 緊密銜接!
Lock your shields. Stay as one.
穩住!
Hold!
穩住! 盾牌銜接起來!
Hold! As one!
做得好
Well done.
穩住! 下面!
Hold. Down low!
好!
Yes!
賀格!
Hagen!
一隊去移戰車! 一隊...跟我來!
This column to the chariot! This column stay with me!
快點!
Quickly!
- 去前面! - 快!
- Get out there. - Hurry!
馬西墨斯!
Maximus!
單排隊形! 排成一排!
Single column! Single column!
我們贏了!
We win!
我對歷史不太清楚 卡西亞斯
My history's a little hazy, Cassius,
不過應該是野蠻人打輸了迦太基戰役吧?
but shouldn't the barbarians lose the battle of Can'thage?
是的 陛下
Yes, sire.
請見諒 陛下
Forgive me, sire.
沒關係 我喜歡驚喜
No, I rather enjoy surprises.
他是誰?
Who is he?
他們叫他做西班牙人 陛下
They call him the Spaniard, sire.
我想見見他
I think I'll meet him.
是 陛下
Yes, sire.
為野蠻人歡呼!
Hail to the barbarians!
前進! 嚴密戒備!
Forward! Arms at ready!
放下武器!
Drop your weapons.
皇帝要見你 角鬥士
Gladiator, the Emperor has asked for you.
我隨時聽候差遣
I am at the Emperor's service.
起身 起身
Rise. Rise.
西班牙人 你果然名不虛傳
Your fame is well deserved, Spaniard.
我相信其他的角鬥士都不是你的對手
I don't think there's ever been a gladiator to match you.
這位年輕人堅持你是赫克托轉世
As for this young man, he insists you are Hector reborn.
還是你是大力神的化身?
Or was it Hercules?
你為何不表明身份 告訴大家你的真名?
Why doesn't the hero reveal himself and tell us all your real name?
你總有名字吧?
You do have a name.
"角鬥士"就是我的名字
My name is Gladiator.
你竟敢背對著我? 奴隸!
How dare you show your back to me? Slave!
脫掉頭盔 告訴我你的名字
You will remove your helmet and tell me your name.
我叫馬西墨斯德西斯梅裡丟斯
My name is Maximus Decimus Meridius,
北方軍隊的指揮官
commander of the armies of the north,
菲力克斯軍團的將軍
general of the Felix Legions,
真正的皇帝馬可·奧勒留忠心的僕人
loyal servant to the true emperor, Marcus Aurelius,
兒子被人謀殺
father to a murdered son,
妻子遭人殺害...
husband to a murdered wife,
不管今生或來世 我定會為他們復仇
and I will have my vengeance, in this life or the next.
衛兵!
Arms!
活! 活! 活! 活! 活! 活!
Live! Live! Live! Live!
- 活 活 活 - 活 活 活
- Live! Live! Live! Live! - Live! Live! Live! Live!
衛兵 退下!
Arms, at rest!
- 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯! - 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯!
- Maximus! Maximus! Maximus! - Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
父親
Father.
他怎麼還活著?
Why is he still alive?
我不知道
I don't know.
他應該早就死了
He shouldn't be alive.
實在讓人煩惱
It vexes me.
我非常生氣
I'm terribly vexed.
我只是做了不得不做的事
I did what I had to do.
要是按照父親的意願 羅馬早就解體了
If Father had had his way, the empire would have been torn apart.
你明白的 是嗎?
You do see that.
是的
Yes.
你看到他的時候有何感覺?
What did you feel when you saw him?
沒有任何感覺
I felt nothing.
看來他傷得你很深 對不對?
He wounded you deeply, didn't he?
我傷害他更深
No more than I wounded him.
在日耳曼的時候他們說謊
They lied to me in Germania.
他們告訴我他已經死了
They told me he was dead.
他們騙我 即是不尊重我
If they lie to me, they don't respect me.
既然如此 他們又怎麼可能愛我?
If they don't respect me, how can they ever love me?
那麼你必須讓軍團瞭解...
Then you must let the legions know
他們的背叛行為一定會受到懲罰
their treachery will not go unpunished.
可憐的姐姐
Poor sister.
我絕對不想與你為敵
I wouldn't want to be your enemy.
你打算怎麼做?
What will you do?
出來!
This way.
貴婦人付高價是為了讓英勇的角鬥士取悅她
Rich matrons pay well to be pleasured by the bravest champions.
我知道你弟弟會派刺客來
I knew your brother would send assassins.
但我沒想到他會派最好的來
I didn't realize he would send his best.
馬西墨斯 他毫不知情
Maximus, he doesn't know.
我的家人被釘在十字架上活活燒死
My family was burnt and crucified while they were still alive.
- 我真的不知情... - 別對我撒謊!
- I knew nothing... - Don't lie to me!
我為他們哭泣
I wept for them.
就像你為你父親哭泣?
As you wept for your father? As you wept for your father?
自從我父親去世後 我便生活在恐懼之中
I have been living in a prison of fear since that day.
因為害怕自己的弟弟而無法哀悼自己的父親
To be unable to mourn your father for fear of your brother.
因為自己的兒子也是王位繼承人
To live in terror every moment of every day,
我時時刻刻都生活在恐懼之中
because your son is heir to the throne.
我有哭過
I have wept.
我兒子是無辜的
My son was innocent.
我兒子也是
So is mine.
難道非得用我兒子的命來換取你的信任?
Must my son die, too, before you'll trust me?
我是否信任你又有何區別?
What does it matter if I trust you or not?
你難道不明白? 神已經寬恕你了
The gods have spared you. Don't you understand?
今天我看見了比羅馬皇帝還要有權力的奴隸
Today I saw a slave become more powerful than the emperor of Rome.
諸神已經寬恕我了?
The gods have spared me?
因為他們的憐憫 我才有娛樂觀眾的力量!
I am at their mercy, with the power only to amuse a mob.
那就是力量
That is power.
觀眾代表著羅馬
The mob is Rome.
康莫德斯控制了他們就等於掌控了一切
And while Commodus controls them, he controls everything.
聽我說
Listen to me.
元老院的大多數人都是我弟弟的敵人
My brother has enemies, most of all in the Senate.
只是當人民都支持他的時候:
But while the people follow him,
沒有人敢和他正面衝突 除了你
no one would dare stand up to him until you.
他們反對他 卻什麼事都不做
They oppose him, yet they do nothing.
有些政治家為羅馬奉獻出全部的心力
There are some politicians who have dedicated their lives to Rome.
他們有個領袖
One man above all.
如果我出面安排 你願意和他見面嗎?
If I can arrange it, will you meet him?
你到底明不明白?
Do you not understand?
我只是個奴隸 隨時隨地都有可能喪命
I may die in this cell tonight, or in the arena tomorrow. I am a slave!
我又能改變些什麼呢?
What possible difference can I make?
這個人有和你一樣的目的
This man wants what you want.
那就讓他去殺了康莫德斯!
Then have him kill Commodus!
我曾經認識一個人...
I knew a man once,
一個高尚的人
a noble man.
他不但有原則...而且還敬愛我的父親
A man of principle who loved my father,
我的父親也愛他
and my father loved him.
這個人為羅馬貢獻良多
This man served Rome well.
那人已經死了
That man is gone.
你弟弟干的很成功
Your brother did his work well.
讓我幫你
Let me help you.
對 你能幫我
Yes, you can help me.
忘了我們曾經相識...再也不要來這裡看我
Forget you ever knew me, never come here again.
守衛 這位夫人要離開了
Guard! The lady is finished with me.
你叫什麼名字?
What's your name?
朱利安克拉蘇
Julian Crassus.
名字?
Name?
馬可斯 陛下
Marcus, sire.
跟我父親同名
My father's name.
他們在發現馬西墨斯逃走時
They must have known of Maximus' escape,
一定可以找到他們四個的屍體
when they found the bodies of the four men.
他們以為是野蠻人突襲
They thought it was a barbarian raid.
他們是好人 陛下 他們忠於皇上
These are good men, sire. Loyal to the Emperor.
搭箭!
Load your arrows!
準備放箭!
Prepare to fire!
又或者是你知道...
Then perhaps it was you who knew,
而不告訴我
and never told me.
- 我並不知道 - 你不知道?
- I didn't know. - You didn't know?
但將軍永遠有控制權
But a general is always in control.
永遠是命令者 不是嗎?
Always in command, isn't he?
是的 凱撒
Yes, Caesar.
那下命令吧 快說
Then give the command. Say it.
放箭
Fire.
馬西墨斯
Maximus.
你指揮過軍團? 你打過很多勝仗?
You commanded legions? You had many victories?
- 是的 - 在日耳曼?
- Yes. - In Germania?
在很多國家
In many countries.
將軍
General.
你已經出名了
You have a great name.
在殺你之前他得先羞辱你的名聲
He must kill your name before he kills you.
沒錯
Yes, at the far end.
- 蓋爾斯議員 - 你好
- Senator Gaius. - Hello.
格瑞克斯議員
Senator Gracchus.
很難得看見你出現在這種龍蛇混雜的地方
Don't often see you enjoying the pleasures of the vulgar crowd.
我不會假裝和人民打成一片
I don't pretend to be a man of the people, Senator,
但我會做個為人民說話的議員
but I do try to be a man for the people.
- 凱撒! 凱撒! 凱撒! 凱撒! - 凱撒! 凱撒! 凱撒! 凱撒!
- Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! - Caesar! Caesar! Caesar! Caesar!
羅馬的人民!
People of Rome!
今天是安提俄克戰役的第四天
On the fourth day ofAntioch,
同時也是競技慶典的第64天
we can celebrate the 64th day of the games.
在他的仁慈下
And in his majestic charity,
皇帝決定賜予羅馬人民...
the Emperor has deigned this day to favor the people of Rome
一場歷史性的決戰
with an historical final match.
在退休五年後...重回競技場
Returning to the Colosseum today, after five years in retirement,
凱撒很高興為大家請到...
Caesar is pleased to bring you
羅馬歷史上...
the only undefeated champion
唯一的不敗冠軍...
in Roman history,
來自高盧的傳奇的底格里斯!
the legendary Tigris of Gaul!
他太清楚該如何操縱觀眾
He knows too well how to manipulate the mob.
馬可·奧勒留的夢想是建立一個全新的羅馬 普羅西莫
Marcus Aurelius had a dream that was Rome, Proximo.
但新羅馬不應該是這樣的!
This is not it. This is not it!
馬可·奧勒留已經死了 馬西墨斯
Marcus Aurelius is dead, Maximus.
我們只是凡夫俗子 一切終歸塵土
We mortals are but shadows and dust.
一切終歸塵土 馬西墨斯
Shadows and dust, Maximus!
讓我們隆重介紹...
Representing the training lyceum ofAntonius Proximo,
代表普羅西莫訓練會館的...
Caesar is proud to give you
馬西墨斯!
Aelius Maximus!
他們把他當成自己人 敞開雙臂歡迎他
They embrace him like he's one of their own.
觀眾是很善變的 弟弟 不出一個月就會忘記他的
The mob is fickle, brother. He'll be forgotten in a month.
錯了 用不了那麼久
No, much sooner than that.
一切都安排好了
It's been arranged.
角鬥士向你致敬
We who are about to die salute you.
我們支持你 馬西墨斯!
We're with you, Maximus!
打敗他!
Fight on, finish it!
用力拉!
Pull, pull!
放開! 放開!
Loose! Loose!
- 殺了他! - 殺!
- Gut him! - Kill!
- 殺! 殺! 殺! 殺! - 殺! 殺! 殺! 殺!
- Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill! - Kill! Kill! Kill! Kill!
- 殺! - 殺!
- Kill! - Kill!
仁慈的馬西墨斯!
Maximus the Merciful!
- 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯! - 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯!
- Maximus! Maximus! Maximus! - Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
衛兵 前進 攻擊隊形!
Forward, arms at ready!
我該拿你怎麼辦?
What am I going to do with you?
為什麼你...不去死
You simply won't die.
我們之間的差異真有這麼大嗎?
Are we so different, you and I?
必要時你也殺人...就像我一樣
You take life when you have to, as I do.
只剩下一個人我非殺不可 然後我的責任就完成了
I have only one more life to take. Then it is done.
那現在就動手啊
Then take it now.
他們告訴我你兒子...
They tell me your son
在被釘上十字架的時候...象女孩子一樣在尖叫
squealed like a girl when they nailed him to the cross.
還有你妻子...
And your wife
在被他們蹂躪的時候...
moaned like a whore
象妓女一樣在呻吟...
when they ravaged her again and again
一次又一次...呻吟著
and again.
你呼風喚雨的日子很快就要結束了
The time for honoring yourself will soon be at an end,
陛下
Highness.
將軍!
General! General!
- 將軍! - 西斯洛!
- General! - Cicero!
- 將軍! - 軍隊在哪裡紮營?
- General! - Where are you camped?
在奧斯亞
Ostia.
- 我們愛你 馬西墨斯! - 讚美勝利者!
- We love you, Maximus! - Praise the victor!
告訴大家我還活著 來找我
Tell the men their general lives. Find me.
- 快走! - 來找我!
- Move along! - Find me!
他們可以聽到你的祈禱嗎?
Can they hear you?
- 誰? - 你在黃泉的家人
- Who? - Your family, in the afterlife.
- 會的 - 你跟他們說什麼?
- Yes. - What do you say to them?
對我的兒子
To my boy,
我告訴他我們很快就能見面了
I tell him I will see him again soon,
騎馬的時候記得腳跟要壓低點
and to keep his heels down when he's riding his horse.
對我妻子...
To my wife,
那不關你的事
that is not your business.
現在觀眾反而敬愛馬西墨斯的仁慈
And now they love Maximus for his mercy.
因此我更不能殺他 不然就會顯得我更殘暴
So I can'tjust kill him, or it makes me even more unmerciful.
這整件事簡直就像場惡夢
The whole thing is like some great nightmare.
他是在公然向你挑戰
He is defying you.
他每一次的勝利都是種反抗的舉動
His every victory is an act of defiance.
觀眾和元老院議員們都看到了
The mob sees this, and so do the Senate.
只要他存在一天 他們就會越來越大膽
Every day he lives, they grow bolder.
- 殺了他 - 不行
- Kill him. - No.
我不會幫他成為烈士
I will not make a martyr of him.
我今天去國會...
When I went to the Senate today,
特意告訴他們 我用了穀物貯備來支付競技賽
I purposefully told them about using the grain reserves to pay for the games.
你記得發生什麼事嗎?
And did you note what happened?
- 沒什麼 - 對 什麼都沒發生
- Nothing. - Exactly. Nothing.
一句抗議都沒有
Not a single word of protest.
連傲慢的格瑞克斯議員也沒出聲
Even the insolent Senator Gracchus was silent as a mouse.
為什麼?
Why?
我聽說有一種海蛇
I have been told of a certain sea snake
用非常特別的方法來誘捕獵物
which has a very unusual method of attracting its prey.
它會假裝受傷 躺在海底
It will lie at the bottom of the ocean as ifwounded.
然後敵人接近...
接著它的敵人會漸漸的靠近
Then its enemies will approach,
它會繼續躺著不動
and yet it will lie quite still.
接著敵人會開始慢慢的咬它
And then its enemies will take little bites of it,
但它還是...一動不動
and yet it remains still.
那麼
So,
我們要不動聲色...
we will lie still,
耐心等待我們的敵人上鉤
and let our enemies come to us and nibble.
讓所有的議員也自投羅網
Have every senator followed.
西斯洛 我的老朋友
Cicero, my old friend.
我以為再也見不到你了
I thought perhaps I'd seen you for the last time.
- 我以為你死了 - 差不多
- I thought you were dead. - Close.
軍團駐紮在奧斯亞有多久了?
How long have the men been in Ostia?
整個冬季
All winter.
- 他們的狀況如何? ? - 整天吃飽了 無所事事
- And how do they look? - Fat and bored.
- 指揮官是誰? - 從羅馬來的白癡
- Who's in command? - Some fool from Rome.
他們最快要什麼時候才能準備好?
How soon do you think they could be ready to fight?
為了你 明天
For you, tomorrow.
有件事我需要你幫忙
I need you to do something for me.
各位 快來看
Come, see, witness.
如果你沒去競技場的話 你能在這裡看見當時的情景
If you haven't been in the arena, you can see the show here.
馬西墨斯快要打敗我們的皇帝康莫德斯了 我們該怎麼辦?
Giant Maximus is defeating our emperor, Commodus.
他藐視每一個人
What are we to do? He's just defying everyone,
我們該怎麼辦?
by doing this to him, they do...
啊! 我的天啊!
My goodness!
- 他贏了! - 讓路!
- He got him, he's defeated. - Give way!
公主陛下? 我在凡度巴納侍奉過你父親
My lady? I served your father at Vindobona.
- 退後 - 我的夫人
- Back. - My lady.
我在凡度巴納服侍過你父親
I served your father at Vindobona.
退後!
Back!
我也服侍過馬西墨斯將軍 我現在還為他服務
And I served General Maximus. I serve him still.
停下來
Stop. Stop.
停!
Stop!
退下
Stand back.
將軍讓我帶個口信 他願意見你說的政治家
The general sends word, he will meet your politician.
- 士兵 獎賞你的忠誠 - 謝謝 夫人
- For your loyalty, soldier. - Thank you, my lady.
出去吧
Leave us.
格瑞克斯議員
Senator Gracchus.
將軍
General.
我希望今天我來這裡能夠...
I hope my coming here today is evidence enough
使你信任我
that you can trust me.
- 元老院和你的立場一致? - 元老院?
- The Senate is with you? - The Senate?
是的 我能代表他們
Yes. I can speak for them.
你能幫我獲得自由偷偷把我運出羅馬嗎?
You can buy my freedom and smuggle me out of Rome?
你打算幹什麼?
To what end?
把我送到城外去
Get me outside the city walls.
準備好馬匹讓我去奧斯亞 我的軍隊在那裡紮營
Have fresh horses ready to take me to Ostia. My army is encamped there.
我會在第二天傍晚率領五千名士兵回來
By nightfall of the second day, I shall return at the head of 5, 000 men.
但軍團的新指揮官
But the legions all have new commanders,
全都效忠於康莫德斯
loyal to Commodus.
只要我的部下看到我還活你就知道他們效忠誰了
Let my men see me alive, and you shall see where their loyalties lie.
簡直太瘋狂了
This is madness.
百年來羅馬軍隊從未進入過首都
No Roman army has entered the capital in 100 years.
我不願意引狼入室!
I will not trade one dictatorship for another!
議員 已經沒時間商量權宜辦法了
The time for half measures and talk is over, Senator.
在你光榮的政變之後又將如何?
And after your glorious coup, what then?
你會帶著五千名士兵離開羅馬?
You'll take your 5, 000 warriors and leave?
我會離開
I will leave.
士兵們會留下來保護你們
The soldiers will stay for your protection,
受元老院的指揮
under the command of the Senate.
換言之
So,
一旦羅馬被你控制以後...你會將它交還給人民?
once all of Rome is yours, you'll just give it back to the people?
告訴我原因
Tell me why.
因為那是某人臨死前最後的期望
Because that was the last wish of a dying man.
我會殺了康莫德斯
I will kill Commodus.
羅馬的命運就交給你了
The fate of Rome I leave to you.
馬可·奧勒留信任你
Marcus Aurelius trusted you.
他的女兒信任你
His daughter trusts you.
我也會信任你
I will trust you.
但我們時間緊迫
But we have little time.
給我兩天時間...
Give me two days,
我會想辦法使你獲得自由
and I will buy your freedom.
而你...
And you,
你千萬要活下去
you stay alive,
否則我就死定了
or I'll be dead.
我們得走了
Now we must go.
他會在等你 站在鬥獸場腳下
He'll be waiting for you. Stand at the foot of the colossus.
他會找到你
He'll find you.
不可能成功的
It won't work.
皇帝對一切都瞭如指掌
The Emperor knows too much.
對我來說...
And as for me,
形勢越來越危險了
it's becoming dangerous.
我回來後會酬謝你的
You'll be paid on my return.
我向你保證
I give you my word.
保證? 你不回來的話怎麼辦呢
Your word? What if you don't return?
你還記得信任別人的感覺嗎 普羅西莫?
Do you remember what it was to have trust, Proximo?
信任?
Trust?
有誰值得我信任?
Who am I to trust?
- 我會殺死康莫德斯 - 對我有什麼好處?
- I will kill Commodus. - Why would I want that?
他給我帶來財富
He makes me rich.
我知道你是個信守承諾的人 將軍
I know that you are a man of your word, General.
我也知道你願意為榮譽而死
I know that you would die for honor.
你願意為羅馬而犧牲
You would die for Rome.
願意為祖先的名譽而死
You would die for the memory of your ancestors.
但我 換個角度說...
But I, on the other hand,
我不過是個表演藝人
I'm an entertainer.
守衛!
Guard!
他殺了還你自由的那個人
He killed the man who set you free.
大人 是禁衛軍
Praetorians, master.
停!
Halt!
你去哪裡了?
Where have you been?
我派人去找你
I sent for you.
弟弟 別疑神疑鬼了
Please, brother.
什麼事讓你煩心?
What's troubling you?
格瑞克斯是不是有了新愛人?
Does Gracchus have a new lover?
我不知道
I don't know.
我以為你見過他
I thought you'd seen him.
他像傷寒一樣影響著每個人
He infects everyone like a putrid fever.
為羅馬著想 必須要犧牲元老院
For the health of Rome, the Senate must be bled.
他也不能倖免
And he will bleed, too.
時機成熟了
Very soon.
不要選在今晚
But not tonight.
還記得父親曾說過的話嗎?
Do you remember what our father said once?
"一場夢...
"It's a dream,
生活就是...
"a frightful dream,
一場噩夢"
"life is."
你覺得他說的對嗎?
Do you think that's true?
我不知道
I don't know.
我認為是真的
I think it is.
而我只能和你分享
And I have only you to share it with.
張開嘴
Open your mouth.
你知道我愛你
You know I love you.
我也愛你
And I love you.
出去 滾出去!
Out. Get out!
快點!
Move!
恭喜你 將軍
Congratulations, General.
你的朋友很擅於說服別人
You've got very persuasive friends.
我弟弟已經逮捕了格瑞克斯
My brother has had Gracchus arrested.
我們不能再等下去了 今晚一定得離開
We daren't wait any longer. We must leave tonight.
普羅西莫半夜會來把你帶到大門口
Proximo will come at midnight and take you to the gate.
你的僕人 西斯洛 會帶著馬在那邊等你
Your servant, Cicero, will be waiting there with horses.
- 你一個人安排這一切的嗎? - 是
- You have done all this? - Yes.
你太冒險了
You risk too much.
我有太多的債要還
I have much to pay for.
你並沒有虧欠任何人
You have nothing to pay for.
你愛你的兒子 為了他 你變得十分堅強
You love your son. You're strong for him.
我已經厭倦了
I am tired of being strong.
我弟弟憎恨全世界 尤其是你
My brother hates all the world, and you most of all.
- 因為你父親選了我 - 不
- Because your father chose me. - No.
因為我父親愛你
Because my father loved you.
而我也愛你
And because I loved you.
很久以前的事了
A long time ago.
我變了很多嗎?
Was I very different then?
你以前比較愛笑
You laughed more.
我一直都覺得很寂寞
I have felt alone all my life,
除了跟你一起時
except with you.
我要走了
I must go.
是的
Yes.
那裡
There.
我贏了
And I got you.
現在玩士兵打仗不會晚了點嗎?
Isn't it late to be playing legionnaire?
我不是士兵
I'm not a legionnaire.
- 不是士兵? - 我是角鬥士
- Not a legionnaire? - I'm a gladiator.
角鬥士?
A gladiator?
角鬥士只在競技場裡打鬥
Gladiators only fight in the games.
難道你不想像凱撒朱利葉...那樣當一名出色的羅馬戰士?
Wouldrt you rather be a great Roman warrior like Julius Caesar?
我是馬西墨斯 羅馬的救世主!
I'm Maximus, the savior of Rome!
羅馬的救世主?
The savior of Rome?
是誰說的?
And who said that?
盧修斯在哪裡?
Where's Lucius?
他和皇帝在一起 夫人
He's with the Emperor, my lady.
- 她不可能那樣做 - 不 是真的
- She couldn't. - Yes, she did.
她在籃中拿出來...
She took it from a basket,
她從籃子裡拿出來 把它放在胸口 就在她心臟的正上方
and pressed it to her breast, right here above her heart.
- 它咬在她的胸口上? - 是的
- It bit her in the breast? - Yes.
你知道嗎? 盧修斯 有時候那些皇室的小姐們...
You see, Lucius, sometimes royal ladies
為了愛可以做出一些非常奇怪的事來
behave very strangely and do very odd things in the name of love.
- 我覺得這樣做很愚蠢 - 我也這麼想
- I think it's silly. - So do I.
我也這麼想
So do I.
姐姐 過來加入我們
Sister, join us.
我在念故事給盧修斯聽
I've been reading to dear Lucius.
- 我也在讀 - 沒錯
- I've been reading, too. - Yes.
他是個非常機靈的小男孩 總有一天他會成為了不起的皇帝的
He's a very clever little boy. He'll make a grand emperor one day.
我們在讀偉大的安東尼
We've been reading about the great Mark Antony,
和他在埃及的冒險
and his adventures in Egypt.
還有皇后用蛇自殺的故事
And the queen killed herself with a snake.
我還沒告訴你發生在我們祖先身上的故事
And just wait until you hear what happened to our ancestors.
如果你很乖的話
If you're very good,
明晚我會給你講克勞迪亞斯皇帝的故事
tomorrow night, I'll tell you the story of Emperor Claudius.
他身邊最親近的人...
He was betrayed
背叛了他
by those closest to him.
他的親人
By his own blood.
他們在黑暗的角落裡商議...
They whispered in dark corners
並且在半夜偷偷出去...
and went out late at night,
共同密謀...
and conspired, and conspired.
但皇帝知道他們在策劃陰謀
But the Emperor Claudius knew that they were up to something.
他知道象小蜜蜂一樣忙碌
He knew they were busy little bees.
有天晚上 他和其中一人談話...
And one night he sat down with one of them,
他看著她...
and he looked at her,
然後說...
and he said,
"告訴我你們的計劃...
"Tell me what you've been doing,
忙碌的小蜜蜂
"busy little bee.
不然我會殺死你最親的人...
"Or I shall strike down those dearest to you.
你會看到我身上沾滿他們的鮮血"
"You shall watch as I bathe in their blood."
而皇帝的心都碎了
And the Emperor was heartbroken.
小蜜蜂對他的傷害
The little bee had wounded him more deeply
比任何人都要深
than anyone else could ever have done.
盧修斯 你認為接下來會發生什麼事?
What do you think happened then, Lucius?
我不知道 舅舅
I don't know, Uncle.
小蜜蜂告訴了他所有的事
The little bee told him everything.
開閘 皇上有令!
Open, in the name of the Emperor!
普羅西莫!
Proximo!
開門 我們是奉皇帝的命令來的!
Open the gates, in the name of the Emperor!
普羅西莫!
Proximo!
奉皇帝的命令 開門!
Open the gates!
快開門 普羅西莫!
Open the gates, Proximo.
老頭 你想找死嗎?
Do you want to die, old man?
拿去
Here.
一切準備好了
Everything is prepared.
看來你贏得你的自由了
It seems you have won your freedom.
普羅西莫 當個好人是否會替你惹上麻煩
Proximo, are you in danger of becoming a good man?
- 裘巴 - 反抗皇帝的人都得死!
- Juba. - All enemies of the Emperor die!
開門! 皇帝的命令!
Open the gates!
用力拉!
Pull!
沖! 兩隊人去左邊!
Move! Form a column on the left!
我只需要機會脫身 千萬別做無謂的犧牲
I only need moments, so do not be careless with your lives.
不想被捲入這事的 就回到囚室裡去
If you don't want any part of this, go back to your cells.
我們會留在這裡幫你 馬西墨斯
We'll wait here for you, Maximus.
- 勇氣和榮譽 - 勇氣和榮譽
- Strength and honor. - Strength and honor.
去吧
Go.
勇氣和榮譽
Strength and honor.
瞄準 拉弓!
Aim. Arch your bows!
馬可·奧勒留914-922
普羅西莫
一切終歸塵土
Shadows and dust.
馬西墨斯!
Maximus!
對不起
I'm sorry.
事情都解決了
It's done.
該如何處治我的外甥?
And what of my nephew?
還有他的母親?
And what of his mother?
他們應該面對和她愛人相同的命運嗎?
Should they share her lover's fate?
還是我應該網開一面?
Or should I be merciful?
仁慈的康莫德斯
Commodus the Merciful.
從現在起 盧修斯由我照顧
Lucius will stay with me now.
如果他母親...
And if his mother
用令我不快的眼神看著我...
so much as looks at me
用令我不快的態度對我...
in a manner that displeases me,
他就會死
he will die.
如果她想...抵死不從...
If she decides to be noble,
或者想自殺的話...
and takes her own life,
他會死
he will die.
至於你...
And as for you,
你會愛我...
you will love me,
就像我愛你一樣
as I have loved you.
你會幫我生育下一代 血統純正的繼承人...
You will provide me with an heir of pure blood,
那麼康莫德斯
so that Commodus
和他的子孫...將世世代代統治羅馬
and his progeny will rule for 1, 000 years.
我不夠仁慈嗎?
Am I not merciful?
Am I not merciful!
- 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯! - 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯! 馬西墨斯!
- Maximus! Maximus! Maximus! - Maximus! Maximus! Maximus!
我是軍人 我職責是服從
I'm a soldier. I obey.
沒人可以逼你做你不願意的事
Nothing happens to anyone that he is not fitted by nature to bear.
馬西墨斯!
Maximus.
他們在為你歡呼
They call for you.
一個淪為奴隸的將軍
The general who became a slave.
一個變成角鬥士的奴隸
The slave who became a gladiator.
一個挑戰皇帝的角鬥士
The gladiator who defied an emperor.
一個震撼人心的故事
A striking story.
現在人們想知道故事的結局
Now the people want to know how the story ends.
只有一個出名的死亡才能令人滿意
Only a famous death will do.
還有什麼能比...
And what could be more glorious
在競技場上親自挑戰皇帝來的光榮呢?
than to challenge the Emperor himself in the great arena?
- 你要和我決鬥? - 為什麼不?
- You would fight me? - Why not?
你以為我害怕嗎?
Do you think I'm afraid?
我認為你一生人也在害怕
I think you have been afraid all your life.
不像無敵的馬西墨斯 有誰從來不害怕?
Unlike Maximus the Invincible, who knows no fear?
一個我認識的人曾經說過 "死亡向所有人微笑...
I knew a man who once said, "Death smiles at us all.
人們所能做的就是還以微笑"
"All a man can do is smile back."
我在懷疑
I wonder,
你的朋友在面對死亡時也在微笑嗎?
did your friend smile at his own death?
你要知道
You must know.
他是你父親
He was your father.
我知道 你愛我的父親
You loved my father, I know,
但我也愛他
but so did I.
我們因此是兄弟 不是嗎?
That makes us brothers, doesn't it?
兄弟 對我微笑吧
Smile for me now, brother.
替他穿上盔甲 把傷口遮住
Strap on his armor. Conceal the wound.
成包圍隊形!
Ring formation!
昆塔斯 劍
Quintus, sword.
把你的劍給我!
Give me your sword.
劍! 給我把劍!
Sword! Give me a sword!
收劍入鞘! 收劍入鞘!
Sheathe your swords. Sheathe your swords!
馬西墨斯
Maximus.
昆塔斯
Quintus.
還我的人自由
Free my men.
恢復格瑞克斯議員的職位
Senator Gracchus is to be reinstated.
羅馬的共和是個夢想
There was a dream that was Rome.
它應當被實現
It shall be realized.
這些都是馬可·奧勒留的心願
These are the wishes of Marcus Aurelius.
釋放囚犯 快去
Free the prisoners. Go!
馬西墨斯
Maximus.
盧修斯安全了
Lucius is safe.
去找他們吧
Go to them.
你回到家了
You're home.
羅馬值得一個好人犧牲性命嗎?
Is Rome won'th one good mars life?
我們曾經相信
We believed it once.
那就讓我們再次相信吧
Make us believe it again.
他是羅馬的將士
He was a soldier of Rome.
讓我們給他榮耀
Honor him.
誰願意來幫我一起抬他?
Who will help me carry him?
現在我們都自由了
Now we are free.
我們會再見面的
I will see you again.
不過現在還不是時候
But not yet.
還不是時候
Not yet.